<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Gospell and his maintenance VVherein is shevved, that as it is Gods ordinance, that the Gospell should be preached, so also is it his ordinance, that the ministers and preachers of the Gospell, shall have and receaue tithes, jure divino, by divine right. Herein also is that question concerning the right of personall tithes resolved, and added to this sermon. Preached at a synod of the R. Reverend Father in God the Lord Bishop of Chichester, holden in the Cathedrall Church of Chichester, the 3. of October 1632. By Ro. Johnson, B.D.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Ro. (Robert)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04573</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843537</idno>
  <idno type="VID">8277</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240899575</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 14692</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107845</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99843537e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 754:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Gospell and his maintenance VVherein is shevved, that as it is Gods ordinance, that the Gospell should be preached, so also is it his ordinance, that the ministers and preachers of the Gospell, shall have and receaue tithes, jure divino, by divine right. Herein also is that question concerning the right of personall tithes resolved, and added to this sermon. Preached at a synod of the R. Reverend Father in God the Lord Bishop of Chichester, holden in the Cathedrall Church of Chichester, the 3. of October 1632. By Ro. Johnson, B.D.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Ro. (Robert)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Cotes, for Michal Sparke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8277:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8277:1"/>
            <p>THE GOSPELL AND HIS MAINTENANCE.</p>
            <p>Wherein is shewed, That as it is Gods Ordinance, that the Gospell should be preached, So also is it his Ordinance, that the Ministers and Preachers of the Gospell, shall have and receaue Tithes, <hi>jure Divino,</hi> by Divine right.</p>
            <p>Herein also is that Question concerning the right of Personall Tithes resolved, and added to this Sermon.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>9.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>So hath the Lord ordained, that they which Preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gen. <hi>14.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And Abraham gave Melchizedech, Tithes of all.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gen. <hi>28.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And of that thou shalt give me, I will give the Tenth unto thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Preached at a Synod of the R. Reverend Father in God the Lord Bishop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> holden in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Chichester,</hi> the 3. of <hi>October</hi> 1632.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ro. Johnson, B.D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. Cotes,</hi> for <hi>Michal Sparke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8277:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8277:2"/>
            <head>To the R. Reverend Father in God, RICHARD, Lord Bishop of Chichester.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reverend, we live now in those dayes of which the Apostle spake sixteene hundred yeeres since; That in the last dayes should be perillous times, in which there should be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. lovers of themselves, covetous: and one depends upon the other; They are too covetous, because they love themselves too much. Such are these sacrilegious times we now live in, for Sacriledge hath already in part, and would if it could, devoure <hi>in toto</hi> (like <hi>Asher</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi>) the remaines left unto the Church: <hi>Victa jacet pietas,</hi> Charity and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is banished, <hi>Munus illud antiquum offerendi
<pb facs="tcp:8277:3"/> vertitur in munus auferendi, quò factum est, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siam etiam de reliquiis Decimarum in jus vocari posse, &amp; novas rationes excogitari de stipe, de quotâ parte, de nullâ parte illarum disputare;</hi> giving is now tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to taking away, wherby it is come to passe that the right of the remaines of the Church, (which are Tithes and Offerings) is now cald into Question, and to dispute of some other part, than the tenth, or of no part at all, to bee due to the Ministers of the Gospell by Divine right. For many there are, that say and affirme, Tithes to be due onely <hi>jure positivo humano,</hi> and not <hi>jure Divino,</hi> onely by positive humane law, and not by the Divine Law of God. Wherein they seeme to taxe God with injustice, for that he in his Divine law, hath straightly charged us to preach the Word, and by that law to give us no maintenance for preaching, but must bee beholden only to humane lawes for the same. Indeed wee blesse God for these positive Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane laws for Tithes, because such is the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of these last sacrilegious times, that many men will neither be instructed nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by Divine Law, to pay their Tithes out of a good conscience, and as they ought to do, but must be compelled thereunto by positive
<pb facs="tcp:8277:3"/> humane lawes; but it doth not follow thereby that Tithes are due onely <hi>jure positivo humano,</hi> onely by positive humane lawe, and not by Divine right The Divine Law saith, <hi>Thou shalt not steale,</hi> and the positive humane law saith likewise; thou shalt not steale. But it doth not therefore follow that the positive humane law should abrogate and annihilate the Divine and Morall Law of God It is agreed on by all sides, that by Divine right Ministers must have maintenance for Preaching; And if mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, then either more or lesse, or the same that the Levites had. To allow us more, men now a dayes will not; and to allow us lesse than the Levites had, is to undervalue the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Gospell, which is the ministration of righteousnesse that exceedes in glory, far I say above the ministration of the lawe, which is the ministration of condemnation. If then not more, nor lesse than the Levites had, then the maintenance must be the same, that the Levits had, or nothing at all. Had the Levites Tithes and Offerings? So hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Gospell should live of the Gospell, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 9.14. For if it be granted that they of the law receaved Tithes for their Ministery; then it must needes bee granted,
<pb facs="tcp:8277:4"/> that wee of the Gospell shall receave Tithes much rather. For so saith the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12. <hi>If others</hi> (that is, the Levites) <hi>bee partakers of this power, why not we rather?</hi> as if he should say, If they of the law receaved tithes; shall not we the Ministers of the Gospel much rather? <hi>Know ye not</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>that they which minister about holy things, eate of the things of the Temple? and they that waite at the Altar, are partakers of the Altar?</hi> So hath the Lord ordained, that they which waite at the Altar, and preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospel. Hath the Lord ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the Levites of the law should have tithes and offerings; So hath the Lord ordained that the Ministers of the Gospell should have tithes and offerings: For the Apostle speaking there of the Levits maintenance, concludeth by those words, <hi>so hath the Lord ordained,</hi> that the Ministers portiō should be no lesse than theirs, if not more. For if we can have no lesse, nor no more, then it must be the same that the Levites had, which is the 10. or else nothing. Now for the word <hi>Tenth,</hi> who knows not <hi>quid sit decima? Nempe ex</hi> 10 <hi>partibus una</hi> And this 10 part was instituted by <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 14 20. <hi>Abraham gave Melchiz. tithes of al.</hi> To which the Apostle addeth <hi>Heb</hi> 7 2. <hi>Melchiz. receaved tithes of Abraham.</hi> And it
<pb facs="tcp:8277:4"/> must needes be that he receaved them <hi>de jure,</hi> of right For otherwise <hi>Melchiz.</hi> had not bin more excellent than <hi>Abrahā</hi> of whom he receaved thē. Neither did <hi>Abrahā</hi> pay tithes <hi>jure sacrificii (nullū enim obtulit) sed benedictionis gratiâ;</hi> by right of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice (for hee offered none) but because hee might receave a blessing from <hi>Melchizedeck:</hi> for these 2 cohere, <hi>benedixit Melchizedec, decimas pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Abraham,</hi> Thus then I argue against all sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious persons that gainsay this truth, <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zedeco benedicenti debentur decimae, sed idem jus sub Christo manet; (quia juravit Deus &amp; non poenitebit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Tu es Sacerdos in aeternum secundùm ordinē Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedech, Psa.</hi> 110 <hi>ergo etiam Christo &amp; Sacerdotio ejus, quod non transfertur, sed manet in aeternū, decimae de jure semper debentur; manet semper sub Christo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimarū jus, in quo &amp; per quē, benedicti sumus omnes, &amp; benedictus ipse in secula. Si enim decimae sunt ita Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotio annexae ex instituto Divino, quis vel qualis sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegus eas separabit. Quae enim Deus conjunxit, nemo separet. Sanè vel adversarii nostri, decimarū jus perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sè altercantur, aut Apostolus ad Heb.</hi> 7.8. <hi>non solidè hâc in re instituit. Ʋbi enim Sacerdos ibi decimae. Vivit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos, non auferentur</hi> 10. <hi>vivit Sacerdotiū in aeternū, non auferentur decimae in aeternū. Ergo intelligāt omnes sacrilegi, quòd Deus omnes Abrahami posteros obligavit ut eâdem, quâ decimatus est Lege Abraham, eadem
<pb facs="tcp:8277:5"/> lege atque institutione, omnes ejus posteri decimas suas debent persolvere.</hi> And as the sacred Scriptures maintaine and teach this truth for tithes, so do also many of the Fathers. S. <hi>Ierom</hi> writing on that place of the Gospel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23 23. <hi>Decimatis menthā &amp; anethū, &amp;c.</hi> saith, <hi>Justitiā &amp; misericordiā &amp; fidē propter suā gloriā mādavit Deus, decimas autē propter Sacerdotes.</hi> And S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> also writeth to like purpose concerning tithes and offerings, <hi>Presbyteri ab Altari &amp; sacrificiis non recedant, sed die ac nocte coelestibus rebus ac spiritualibus serviant &amp; decimas tanquā Levitae, ex fructibus terrae accipiant.</hi> Let the Priests &amp; Ministers of the Gospel waite at the Altar and receave tithes, as the Levits did. Therefore are tithes due to the Ministers and Preachers of the Word, <hi>jure Divino,</hi> by Divine right And now my Lord, I thought good out of that respect I owe your Lordship, to addresse the same to your Lordships service and Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage; not doubting but that your Lordship &amp; all well affected Christians herein, will with me defend this truth, that <hi>decima pars, Dei pars est &amp; Ministrorum portio;</hi> the tent part is the Lords part, and his Ministers portion. And so leaving your Lordship to the Divine providence, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies rest, at your Lordships service to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ro. Johnson.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8277:5"/>
            <head>THE GOSPELL And his maintenance.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Text. <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 9.14.</hi>
                  </bibl> So hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N every Worke there must be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Time and a Tempestivity, or season observed: a time which is, <hi>mensura actionum,</hi> that which measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all our actions, and then a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestivity or season, which may bee called <hi>Sal actionum,</hi> that which sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soneth all our actions (for whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is unseasonable, is unpleasant.) And as in all other workes, so also in this great Worke of the Lord, the preaching and dispensing of the Word; there must be observed a time, and tempestivity or season, that is, Text and Time must have congruity each with other. We are heere now meet at a Synod or Assembly of learned Men, and Preachers of the Gospel, and what fitter subject can I treate of, than of the Gospell, and the maintenance, that doth belong unto the Preachers thereof? For as a Father truly said, <hi>Ʋt Salus non sine Verbo, nec sine Prophetâ Verbum; sic sine authoramento suo, nec Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetas, nec Prophetarum scholas, diu fore certum est:</hi> As there is no Faith and Salvation without the Word, nor Word preached without the Prophets: So without maintenance neither the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8277:6"/> nor Schooles of the Prophets can long continue. Therefore saith my Text, <hi>Hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell.</hi> Preaching is the Lords ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: and maintenance for Preaching is also the Lords ordinance: therfore, there is a necessity for both; For God hath ordained them both, <hi>Dominus ordinavit,</hi> the Lord hath ordained, that they which Preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell. First then, there is a necessity of Preaching the Gospell, for so saith S. <hi>Paul, Necessity is laid upon me, and woe is me if I preach not the Gospell.</hi> To this purpose the Lord by the mouth of his Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Ezeck. cap. 33</note> If the watchman blow not the Trumpet, if destruction come upon the people, their blood will I require at the hands of that Prophet. A necessity then wee see lyeth on the Prophet to preach, for the Lord hath also ordained it. And secondly, a necessity also there is of maintenance for the Preachers of the Gospell, because the Lord hath ordained both. As there is a necessity of the one, so also there is of the other. If we preach not the Gospell, we perish in our soules, and if we have not maintenance for preaching, wee perish in our bodies. If we preach not the Gospell, our soules are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to bee lost: and if we shall not have maintenance also for Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, our bodies are in danger to be lost; both then must be had, because it is the Lords ordinance, and because it concernes also both our soules and bodies. <hi>Therefore hath the Lord ordained, &amp;c.</hi> Here then is Gods ordai-nance, which requires two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Preaching of the Gospell.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Maintenance due thereunto.</p>
            <p>In the first, The ordinance for preaching, we may observe who it is that maketh this ordinance, it is the Lord, <hi>Dominus ordinavit,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Lord hath ordained.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> What it is that is ordained, namely two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That the Gospell be preached, for so hath the Lord ordained.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That the Preachers thereof be maintained, for so hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell. Of these in order.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And first wee are to consider, who it is that maketh this ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the Preaching of the Gospell, namely the Lord, <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ordinavit,</hi> It is the Lords ordinance, not mans: both the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Gospell, and the maintenance thereunto belonging:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8277:6"/> It is not <hi>inventum Humanum,</hi> but <hi>institutum Divinum:</hi> Not a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane invention (for then it might cease) but a Divine institution, and ordainance of God that abideth for ever. It is like the laws of the Medes and Persians that after not. It is Gods ordinance that the Gospell should be preached: Whence we may observe, That the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Position. </seg>1</label> preaching of the Gospell is the ordinary meanes that God hath appointed to call us to salvation. So hath the Lord ordained, &amp;c. So the Apostle cals the Gospell <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the power of God to Salvation, to every one that doth believe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the same. And this is the Heavenly vocation and calling, as the Apostle saith, 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2, 14. <hi>He called you by our Gospell, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the glory of our Lord Iesus Christ.</hi> The Apostle cals it our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell, in respect of the preaching thereof. So saith <hi>Aretius</hi> on that place, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Dei est, &amp; Pauli est Evangelium,</hi> It is Gods Gospell, and it is <hi>Pauls</hi> Gospell also: <hi>Dei est Evangelium tanquam authoris, Pauli est, ut ejus praedicatio ei commissa fuerat:</hi> It is Gods Gospell, as hee is the author of it, it is <hi>Pauls</hi> Gospell, as the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thereof it committed unto him.</p>
            <p>This is that immortall seed we carry about, in earthly vessels, and that syncere milke, whereby our soules are nourished up to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. From hence the Gospell hath these severall names, titles and attributes, to shew the efficacy and power thereof. As it is called <hi>Evangelium Dei,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7, <hi>The Gospell of God. Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Christi, Marke</hi> 1.1. <hi>Bonum Dei Verbum, Heb.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Bonum se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Mat.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Evangelium regni, Evangelium salutis, Acts,</hi> 13.13 <hi>Verbum Vita, Phil.</hi> 2. <hi>Verbum reconciliationis,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Verbum Veritatis, Colos.</hi> 1. <hi>Verbum Fidei, Rom.</hi> 10.8. <hi>Doctrina Spiritus.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Gladius Spiritus, Ephes</hi> 6.17. All which titles shew the power and efficacy of the Gospell, and the preaching thereof. For it is this only, that if we be ignorant, can instruct us. If out of the way, it will bring us home. If out of order, this will reforme us. If in heavinesse, this will comfort vs. If dull, this will quicken us. If cold, this will inflame us. Therefore S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> called it a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of Heavenly wisdome, wherein are all true contents for the Soule of man. And the same Father also in his Booke <hi>De duplici Martyrio,</hi> saith, <hi>Nullus est hominum morbus, cui Evangelium praesens remedium non suppeditat.</hi> There is no disease in the soule of man, but there is a remedy for the same in the Gospell. <hi>Tolle, lege, Tolle,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8277:7"/> lege.</hi> Take up and reade, take up and reade the Gospell, (for unto that was the direction,) was it said to S. <hi>Austin</hi> by a supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall voyce, <hi>li. Conf.</hi> 8 <hi>e.</hi> 12. By reading whereof, he became of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichee, a true orthodox Christian, and a strong pillar in the Church of God. This is Gods ordinance, for God hath ordained it, and it is for his glory, and mens salvation: whence we are againe to observe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Position. </seg>2</label> The necessity of Preaching the Gospell. <hi>So hath the Lord ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that they which preach the Gospel, &amp;c. Dominus ordinavit,</hi> saith the Text, therefore necessary. Yea so necessary is it, that our soules cannot live without it, no more than the body can live without food. And as Christ said to <hi>Martha, unum hoc necessarium,</hi> this one thing is necessary: so preaching of the Gospell is the most necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing of all others. If the body wants meat, it dyes: if the soule wants this Heavenly <hi>Manna,</hi> it dyes also. For this is that <hi>Manna</hi> &amp; <hi>Cibus</hi> feeding our soules in this life, to that which is to come. Therefore <hi>Dominus ordinavit,</hi> the Lord had ordained that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell should be Preached. From whence I observe this 3. Position.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Position. </seg>3</label> The dignity and excellency of the office of Preaching. It is not such a meane and base calling, as many count it (that cals us Priests in scorne) seeing our blessed Saviour Christ himselfe tooke on him the office of a Preacher, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.3. Iesus went about all Citties and Townes preaching the Gospell, and healing every sicknesse, and disease amongst the people. From hence, that is, from the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and excellency of their office, are they called <hi>Seers, Saviours, Chariots of Israel, Planters, Waterers, Builders, Stewards, Watchmen Souldiers, Nurces, Friends of God, Workers together with God, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensers of the secrets of God, Prophets, Angels,</hi> and other such like titles of all reverence and honour. And this is Gods ordainance, that so it should be; for <hi>Dominus ordinavit,</hi> saith the text, the Lord hath ordained it, &amp;c. But alas, Brethren, though preaching the Gospell be Gods ordainance, and though it be so necessary, that it concerne our salvation; and though the dignity and excellency of it bee so great; yet notwithstanding how is preaching this ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God neglected and despised? For what acceptance doth it find here, but foolishnesse of preaching, homlines of Sacraments, a militant Church, a despised profession? And the preachers of the Gospel, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the off-scowring of the world. When yet indeed, and in true judgement, it is here you see in my Text,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8277:7"/> Gods ordainance, and this foolishnesse of preaching the power of God to salvation. These mute letters, the lively oracles of God, this despised profession, the meanes of our peace and reconciliation with God: this Church the Kings daughter, all glorious within; this Crosse, the Banner of Victory, and this profession heaven upon earth. Which things being so, it might cause and move any man, to set a better estimate on the Gospel, and the Ministers, and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers thereof. <hi>Sic aestimet,</hi> saith the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>Let a man so esteeme us, as the Ministers of Christ, and Stewards of the secrets of God.</hi> But alas, such is the iniquity of these times; that as the shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow went 10. degrees back in the daies of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> so 10. deg. do the shaddows of Christ, I meane his ministers go back in their esteeme. We may see in some Parishes strange behaviour towards their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the Gospell: A drunken companion bearding Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters; a contentious Incendiary vexing him with continuall sutes and actions; a whispering tale-bearer, casting false aspersions and slanders on him; an obstinate Papist calling us hereticks, and this is the estimate that this world sets on us. We Preach, we Pray, we Study, we spend our time, our braines, our strenght, our heate, our blood, our health and (in a sense) our lives to save their soules, that care not for our bodies. Men sucke our Milke like Mules, and then kicke us with their heeles, nay, even treade and trample us under their feet. Thus are we gone 10. degrees backe in our esteeme; so are we also gone 20. degrees back in our ma<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntenance for the most part of us. For sacriledge hath so pulled and fleeced many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, that they are like <hi>Menalca's</hi> sheep, <hi>Vix ossibus haerent:</hi> wheras a Lay-man runs like a Mathematicall line in wealth, <hi>ad infinitum:</hi> onely the Clergy must be bound to their pittance, to their compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency. These sacrilegious men that rob the Church are <hi>impit Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pezitae</hi> (as one saith) <hi>quibus lucrum est pietas, lucrum est Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: Qui Evangelium praedicant, ex Evangelio non vivunt. Proh du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram conditionem plerorum{que} Ministrorum, non sufficit ad victum, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum vel Petrum adultis exponere in Ecclesia, nisi jugiter etiam Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiū pueris exposuerint in scholâ! exclamandum est profectò cum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Theologo, Aut hoc non est Evangelium, aut qui tam Scythice nos tractant, non sunt Evangelici.</hi> For to returne to the Text: the Lord hath ordained that they which preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell. It were pitty therefore, nay, impiety, that Religion:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8277:8"/> should give way to sacriledge, and Christ to Mammon, to destroy the Church and the Inheritance thereof, which are Tithes, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, which God hath ordained and established by Divine right. For if by Divine right (that is, by Law and Gospell) the Ministers and Preachers must have maintenance: I know no other mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, nor can reade of no other maintenance in the whole Bible than Tithes and Offerings, which are established both by Law and Gospell.</p>
            <p>First by the Law: For our Saviour came not to destroy the Law, but to fulfill the same; especially if it bee a morall Law as this is. Those Tithes then that were due by the morall Law of Moses; Christ and his Apostles did not disanull, but rather put life unto them. Yet wee may plainely discerne many enemies against this truth, and especially three sort of men, that joyne in this sacriledge of robbing Gods Church in Tithes; Atheists, Papists and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants onely in shew: The Atheist, because he hath no religion, he will have all the Tithes: The Papist disliking the present Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, thinkes in conscience, he may keepe Tithes <hi>in Custodiam,</hi> into his owne custody: though perhaps give something of them to his Priests, and keepe the rest for himselfe: And the third thinkes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely, that <hi>paupertas nutrix Religionis,</hi> that poverty in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, is the onely nurse of Religion:<note n="*" place="margin">What hee gives shall bee malevolence by way of Almes.</note> and so layes fast hold on Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, which are and ever were the Lords part, and his Ministers portion. The Church is free, and ever had his freehold and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, that is, Tithes and Offerings, both before the Law, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law and under the Gospell. From whence I collect this fourth position.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Position. </seg>4</label> That Tithes the Churches inheritances are due to the Ministers of the Gospell, <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> by Divine right, that is, by Law and Gospell. And that this is true, we prove it, because <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, because God hath said it in his Scriptures, which cannot lye. Now in Divine matters, we are to consider <hi>quis dixit,</hi> who sayes it, namely God &amp; his Scriptures, and so wee ought <hi>acquiescere,</hi> to sit down and be still. But in humane matters indeed we are to weigh, <hi>Quid &amp; quo jure dictum,</hi> what is said, and by what right, and in these, there can be no simple truth. If then it bee proved that Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes are due to the Ministers of the Gospell, <hi>jure Divino,</hi> by divine right, both by Law and Gospell, this shall satisfie all honest and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8277:8"/> well affected Christians in this truth. But if any bee contentious, we have no such custome, nor the Churches of God. In the mouth of two or three witnesses, every truth shall be established. First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> then we reade in <hi>Genesis,</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithfull payd Tithes to <hi>Melchizedeck. Gen.</hi> 14.20. and that was before <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies</hi> time. For <hi>Levi,</hi> saith the Apostle, paid Tithes in <hi>Abraham.</hi> And if <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> be a Priest for ever, and that Priesthood bee esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in Christ for ever, and continue also for ever. But Christs Priesthood remaineth also for ever. <hi>(Thou art a Priest for ever after the order of Melchizedeck.)</hi> Therefore the maintenance belonging to the same Priesthood, remaineth also for ever. To this purpose, the Apostle saith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Here, men which dye receave Tithes;</hi> but there he, (that is, Christ) receaveth them, of whom it is said, that, he liveth. Secondly, paying Tithes is a moral law still in force, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not to bee abrogated. God himselfe commandeth it by expresse words, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Thou shalt give the Tithe or tenth part of all thy fruits, which grow on the earth, yeare by yeare.</hi> But this is a morall Law not abrogated, but still in force. Therefore are Tithes due by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Divine right. Thirdly, the practise and example of the Fathers and Patriarchs is to bee observed herein. And then we shall find that <hi>Iacob</hi> built a house to God, and gave him Tithes of all he possessed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22. Therefore Tithes ought to bee paid also by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and the practise of the Fathers. Fourthly. If we grant (as wee must needs) that they of the Law receaved Tithes; then it must also be granted that we of the Gospell shall receave them much rather. For so saith the Apostle in this chapter, wherein my Text is, vers. 12. If others be partakers of this power, are not we rather? As if he should say: If they of the Law receaved Tithes, shall not we of the Gospell rather? But they that then waited at the Altar had them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. Therefore we also that now waite at the Altar in time of the Gospell, shall also bee partakers of the Altar, and of all Tithes, rights, and offerings, that thereunto belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth. Had the Priests and Levits in the time of the Law Tithes and Offerings, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sic ordinavit Dominus,</hi> so hath the Lord ordained that they which waite and Preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell. For my Text is the ensuing words to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument before for Tithes, that the Apostle there layeth downe. Had they that waited at the Altar, maintenance? Had the Levites
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8277:9"/> Tithes? So hath the Lord ordained that likewise we the Ministers of the Gospell, which succeede the Levites, should have that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that the Levites had. Fifthly, If the Ministers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell shall not receave the tenth, then either more or lesse than the Levites had: But more they will not give us, and to give us lesse, is to undervalue the Gospell to the Law, and the Ministers of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Gospell to the Ministers of the Law. Six<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hly, As the Law, so also the Gospell commands this truth and duty of paying Tithes in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse words. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Ye Tithe Mint, Anise, and Cummin, and passe over the Law, Iustice, Mercy, and Truth.</hi> These things ought ye to doe, and not to leave the other undone. But all these are morall duties, Iustice, Mercy, and paying of Tithes. Therefore still to be observed. For this word <hi>Oportet,</hi> maketh paying of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes a morall duty. Ye ought not (saith our Saviour) to leave the other undone: If we ought to obey the commandement of Princes, how much more ought we to obey the precepts and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God and our Saviour? And as the Scriptures, so also the Fathers, both of the East and West Churches, doe maintaine this truth.<note place="margin">Orige. Homil. 11 on Numb.</note> S. <hi>Origen</hi> in his 11. Homily upon <hi>Numb.</hi> hath these words: <hi>Quomodo abundat Iusticia nostra, plusquā Scribarū &amp; Pharisaeorum si illi de fructibus terrae suae gust<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re non audent, priusquā primitias Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotibus offerant, &amp; Levitis decima separentur. At ego nihil horum faciens, fructibus terrae abutar, ut Sacerdos nesciat, Levita ignoret, Divinum Altare non sentiat.</hi> How doth our righteousnesse exceed the righteousnesse of the Scribes and Pharisees? If they durst not once to taste of their fruites of the earth, before they had offered their first fruits to the Priests, and their Tiths were separated to the Levites: But I doing none of these things do so abuse the fruits of the earth, that neither the Priest, the Levite, nor Divine Altar are sensible of Tithes. And there also is added: <hi>Hanc ego legem obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari, ettam secundum literam (sicut alia non nulla) necessarium puto.</hi> Againe the same Father writing on the 23 of <hi>Math. v.</hi> 23. on these words, <hi>Ye Tithe Mint, &amp; Cummin, &amp;c.</hi> saith <hi>Hoc est preceptum non minus Christianis, quam Iudaeis necessarium:</hi> This is a Law no lesse necessary for Christians than for the Iewes. S. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> also on the 3. of <hi>Malachy,</hi> on these words: <hi>Ye have spoiled me in Tithes, and offerings,</hi> saith, <hi>Inpenurtâ &amp; fame maledicti estis, quia non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>distis mihi Decimas &amp; Primitias: &amp; quia dum parva subtraxistis,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8277:9"/> &amp; totam abundantiam frugum &amp; possessionum vestrarum perdidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis. Sciatis igitur vos ideo perdidisse abundantiam, quia fraudavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis me meam partem; moneo igitur ut, reddatis mihi mea, &amp; ego restituam vobis vestra.</hi> Ye are cursed in penury and famine, because ye have not given me Tithes and Offerings. And therefore, because ye have taken away from me small things, ye have lost the whole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of your fruits, and possessions. Therefore I admonish you, that you give and render unto me those things that are mine, and I will give and restore unto you those things that are yours. S. <hi>Ierom.</hi> also on that place, saith, <hi>Iustitiam &amp; misericordiam, &amp; fidem prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er suam gloriam mandavit Deus: Decimas autem propter Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes.</hi> S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> also writeth thus of Tithes: <hi>Presbyteri ab Altari &amp; Sacrificiis non recedant: sed die ac nocte coelestibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; spiritualibus serviant, &amp; Decimas, tanquam Levitae, ex fructibus terrae accipiant.</hi> I need not english it to this Auditory. S. <hi>Austin</hi> also hath the words to this effect. <hi>Majores nostri (inquit) ideo copits omnibus abundabant, quia Deo Decimas dederunt, &amp; Caesari censum reddebant: modo autem, quia discessit devotio Dei, accessit indictio fisci.</hi> And thus we see both by Scriptures and Fathers, that, God hath appointed Tithes for the Ministers mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. So hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell should live of the Gospell. If Preachers and Ministers of the Gospell may not have Tithes and Offerings: what will ensue but desolation in the Holy place? and all grow either to blind Idolatry, or flat Paganisme at the last? Therefore let none (except they to whom these holy things doe appertaine) dare lay hands on Gods part and the Churches Inheritance. For it is <hi>sacrilegium,</hi> nay, <hi>sacri furtum,</hi> and <hi>sacri raptum,</hi> plaine theft and robbery against God and his Church. A sharking sacrilegious man thrives backeward: whilest he deceaves God of his due, the tenth part, hee loseth nine parts to himselfe. If ever thou be the fatter for this gravell, or the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher for that, let me come to begge at thy doore. Go on still in thy sacrilegious course. The Prophet <hi>Esayes</hi> prophesie of the Churches estate, in his first chap is now come to passe in these our Dayes: And the daughter of <hi>Sion</hi> shall be left like a cottage in a Vineyard, like a lodge in a Garden of Cucumbers, like a besieged Citty. The Church was once rich, but it was <hi>in diebus illis,</hi> in the golden times, when honesty went in plaine cloathes, and, ostentation durst
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8277:10"/> not give Religion the checkmate: Now they pleade prescription, and proove them their owne by long possession. <hi>Claustra</hi> are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>Plaustra,</hi> religious Houses into Gentlemen-houses. Men rob <hi>aram Dominicam,</hi> to furnish <hi>haram Domesticam,</hi> Gods Altar, to furnish their owne houses; and the fingers of their posterities are therein heavier than their fathers loynes. Heretofore there were builders of Churches, now there are spoylers and robbers of them. When <hi>Cipio</hi> robbed the Temple of <hi>Thelossa,</hi> there was not a man that carried away any of the gold of the Temple, that ever prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after it: I pray you tell me (if especially you note the 2. or 3. generations) how many you know have thrived by the goods of the Church? They go from man to man without rest, like the Arke among the Philistines, which was removed from Ashdod to Gath, from Gath to Eckrom, as if it could finde no place to rest in; but still vexed the people that kept it, till it returned to his owne place in Israel. Oftentimes these Churches livings, being left by Gentlemen to their heires, prove gangrenes to their whole estates: and house being joyned to house so fast, Gods house to their houses, that the fire which begins at the one, oftentimes consumes the other: like that Eagle, which stole a peece of meate from the Altar, carryed a coale with it, that set her owne nest on fire. It may be they can object, they bought these impropriations with their penny. But <hi>Salomon</hi> tels them, it is a snare to a man to usurpe, and de vowre holy things, <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.25. Therefore they ought not to finger these holy things, that are consecrated to the Lord, and thereby to spoyle God, as the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> complaineth in his 3. cha. concerning Tithes and Offerings; Let all sacrilegious Laickes consider these things, whose hands and fingers are belimed with sacriledge and bribery, and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smeered with the price of blood. They whose sacrilegious throates can swallow downe whole Churches, and whose mawes have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured whole Parishes of famished soules. Alas how these men forget to build up the Cedar worke of piety and devotion, and learne onely to paint it over with Vermilion. They white and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the walles of their profession, but the rubbish and cobwebs of sin, sacriledge, bribery, and fimony hangs in the corners of their Conscience. Let them take heed, for a Bible under their arme, or in their houses, will not excuse a false conscience in their bosoms. They loose their prayers, if whilest God hath their knee, the World hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8277:10"/> their conscience. O that they would consider this Text, that these holy things are the Lords and his Ministers, which wayte at the Altar. For as in time of the Law, the Priestes and Levites of the Law had them: so in the time of the Gospel hath the Lord ordained that the Ministers of the Gospell shall have them also. For, <hi>so hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell.</hi> Now to God the Father, God the Sonne, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And now give mee leave also to speake a word of personall Tithes, of the right of them:<note place="margin">Personall Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes due also to Ministers.</note> whether they be also due to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Gospell or not? That is, such Tithes as arise out of any lawfull gaines, gotten by any art, science, mannual occupation, trade or marchandize, whether these personall Tithes be due by Gods Lawes, and by conscience also? My chiefe ayme in this place is (if it be possible) to pull sundry honest Christians out of this unconsci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable sinne, which perhaps many of them never dreamed on.</p>
            <p>The Arguments on which my Position undertaken is grounded, are drawne from these places of Scripture. The 1. place in my Text and the precedent ver. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. <hi>Doe ye not know that they which minister about holy things, live of the things of the Temple, and they which waite at the Altar, are partakers of the Altar? Even so hath the Lord ordained, that they which Preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell should live of the Gospell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The second place of Scripture for the proofe of personall Tithes, is in the Epistle to the Galathians, cap. 6. v. 6. Let him that is taught in the Word, make him that taught him partaker of all his goods. First marke these words; <hi>Let him that is taught and instructed, &amp;c.</hi> whether he be a Nobleman, or a Gentleman, a Husbandman, or a Tradesman, an artificer of the Country, or of the Towne or City (and there is doubtlesse, as much preaching in Cities and Townes, as in country Parishes, where Tithes are paid in kind) Be he what he will be, the Minister and Preacher may justly by Gods Law, demand a portion of that Citizen or Townsmans cleare gaine, that he hath gotten by his art, science, trade, handicraft, or merchandize (by which any lawfull gaine is made) towards his maintenance. The Apostle in expresse words saith it in the places of Scripture before cited, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. &amp; <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.6. The Lord (saith the Apostle) in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. hath ordained, that they which preach the Gospell, should live of the Gospell. But the Gospell is preached to Citizens,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8277:11"/> Townsmen, and Tradsmen, that have many of them no prediall Tithes, as well as it is preached to Husbandmen. Therefore the Parsons, Preachers, and Ministers that have the cure of soules, may justly and lawfully require a maintenance out of their cleere gaines, as well as they may require the tenth from the husbandmen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>1</label> Now there are 2. Questions that will arise here to be considered. First, whether a Minister having a competency in prediall Tithes, (that is, of the profits of the ground) a man that lives by trading, be bound in conscience and justice, to give as much of his cleare gaines as if he had not such a competency in prediall Tithes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>1</label> If every Tradsman must and ought to pay, then whether he be bound to pay a tenth of his cleare gaines.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>1</label> For the 1. I am of opinion that he that heareth Gods Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and is taught in the Word, and is made partaker of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters spirituals, must render unto him his carnals, though the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmans prediall Tithes be neuer so bountifull and sufficient. For what is that to the Tradsmans conscience? And the Apostle proves this in the precedent words in that c. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9, 11. If we have sowen unto you spirituall things, is it a great matter, if we reape your carnall things? And to this purpose, he also saith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. Let him that is taught in the word (whether a Townsman or a Husbandman) minister to him that teacheth him. But these Questions will be best resolved, by propounding and answering the usuall pleas, which many men make against this truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> First, they object. If a Minister have a competent living out of prediall Tithes from the husbandman, then such as live upon tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and marchandize are not bound to allow him maintenance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>1</label> To this I answer, Every Christian whether tradsman or else, ought by Gods Law, and in conscience, to give the Minister his due in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall Tithes, though he have good maintenance from the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in prediall Tithes: For the Apostle in the place before named, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. Let him that is taught, &amp;c. that is, <hi>Every he,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e excepted (unlesse he that hath nothing to give, in which case the Minister, as other men ought to give to that He) every one, I say that heareth the word, and is able to give. For if others give, and thou think by that to be excused; how doest thou obey the Apostles precept, which excludes none but those that have nothing to give? I argue thus: If the Minister might not require maintenance of the Trads<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8277:11"/> because he hath enough from others in prediall Tithes, it would follow then: That if that Minister have a temporall estate of his owne, sufficient to mainteine him, he might not justly demand any Tithes at all: which none that are in their right wits will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme: for who goeth a warfare at his owne cost? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. Who planteth a Vine-yard, and eateth not of the fruit of the Vine? or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milke of the flock? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every man that is made partaker of the Ministers spirituals, must render his carnals. See and consider the 9. cha. of the 1. Epist. to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps the tradsman will reply again, that he payes ij.d. at <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> easter in lieu of his Tithes; which he thinks in conscience to discharge him from further payment.</p>
            <p>To this I answer, that unconscionable Tradsmen, that offerings <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>1</label> are one thing, the 10. part another thing; yet both are holy to the Lord, and are his due, and the payment of the one, doth not abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate or disannull the payment of the other.</p>
            <p>Secondly I answer that unconscionable Tradsman, that if he will <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>1</label> allow God and his Minister but a 2. penny maintenance for feeding his soule: God and the Minister might allow him also in justice, but a 2. penny maintenance for feeding both his body and soule. Let him heare the wise man in this case, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.9. Honour God with thy substance, &amp;c. And the Apostle <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. Let him that is taught in the word, minister unto him that teacheth him in all good things.</p>
            <p>Yet perhaps this sly Tradsman (who by deceaving his Minister, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> deceaveth his own soule) will againe object and say, trade and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession is casuall, and he often looseth more than he gets; why then should not the Minister beare a part in the losses as well as he hath a part in the gaines?</p>
            <p>To this I answer, That the husbandman sometime also looseth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>1</label> and hath not his seed again that he sowed, and yet payes Tithes, else the Minister perhaps in a deare yeare, might perish through want, by that rule of the tradsman. Secondly, it is a fallacy <hi>ex non conces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis;</hi> For the Minister requires no maintenance of the tradsman, whē there is none gotten by him. It is not granted that any Minister of the Gospel will be so unconscionable, as to require Tithes or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of that tradsman that loseth by his trade. The Question is not of his losses, but of his cleare gaines.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8277:12"/>
            <p>Thirdly, The Minister doth not call for his maintenance by way of partner-ship with the tradsman; but as a due for spirituals by Gods Word. And the Ministers paines is as great when he loseth, as the tradsmans paines is when he loseth. In this case (I say) that if the Tradsman be poore, the Minister is bound according to his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to allow him maintenance, and to stirre up others, also to do the like. All these are the objections of a Gadaren, that loves his swine, better than the company of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> Lastly, Sacrilegious men will object, I need not pay personall Tithes, because there is no Law, that can make me confesse them due upon my oath, as I must confesse predicall Tithes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ, </seg>2</label> To this I answer, that personall Tithes are due by Gods Law, and the law of the land also: And though the Law be so remisse, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to put men to their oath for personall Tithes, it doth not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by follow, that they are not due: Yea rather it inferreth, that every good Christian will <hi>ultro,</hi> of his owne accord, in conscience pay his Tithes personall, especially when he is to receave the Sacrament, and is examined by the Minister of his cleare gaine of his personall Tithes. And yet there is a Statute also in the 2. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. Cap. 13. for the pay of thefe personall Tithes; where ye shall find these words. That every person exercising merchandize, bargaining, selling, clothing, handicraft, or other art, &amp;c. shall yearly at the feast of Easter, pay their personall Tithes, the 10. part of his cleare gaines. So to this purpose, a Statute was made in the 27. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. Therefore what is allowed and proved due both by Gods Law, and mans also; man is bound by a double right to observe and keepe.</p>
            <p>Consider these things, and the Lord give you understanding in all things. And now ye that are Bishops and Magistrates, for Gods sake, for his Churches sake, for the poore Ministers sake, for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science sake, and as you would have God to blesse you, and yours; rouse up your spirits, awaken your Christian courage, and set your selves against these wicked and sacrilegious times. See as much as in you lyes, that the Church and the Ministers thereof, have their rights, and portions, which belongs unto them. That so God may open the windowes of Heaven, and powre downe his blessings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; which many times, he hath justly with-held from us, because we have with-held his part from him, which is the <hi>Tenth.</hi> For the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8277:12"/> Tenth part is Gods part, and the Ministers portion. And so prayng God, that every one of us, in our severall callings, may live to the glory of God, the Well-fare of his Church, and Common-weale, and to the comfort also one of another: I end with my dayly Prayers unto God, for the prosperity of Sion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>REcensui concionem hanc, cui titulus est, <hi>The Gospell and his maintenance,</hi> (unàcum Epistola nuncupatoria ad R. in Christo P.D. Episcopum Cicestrensem) in qua nihil reperio bonis moribus, aut sanae doctrinae contrarium, quo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs cum utilitate publica Imprimatur, modò intra septem Menses proximè sequentes; Typis mandetur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex aedibus Fulhamiensibus</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Septem. 2. 1633.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Bray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>